Finding Aid for Institute for Social Research (University of Michigan) records 1936-2013
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- ISR Administrative Files 1949-2013, 40 linear feet
  - Governance Committees 1949-1992
    - Administrative Committee 1949-1992
      - Agendas
        - 1990-1992, 12 folders (Box 5)
          [PR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2022 ]
      - Minutes and Proceedings
        - 1952-1958, 3 folders (Box 5)
        - 1959-1966, 2 folders (Box 6)
          (scattered dates)
        - 1967-1987, 20 folders (Box 6)
      - Notes and Index
        - Notes from meetings 1952-1959 (Box 6)
        - Index to meetings 1976-February 18,1986 (Box 6)
    - Executive Committee 1949-2005
      The Executive Committee minutes and agendas, date from 1949 to 2005 and are arranged in one chronological series. Minutes for meetings prior to 1949 can be found within the records of the Survey Research Center. The minutes offer insight into key issues such as the creation of new centers, the types of researchers ISR sought to recruit and promote, research design and sources of funding, as well as the institute's relationships with the university. There are occasionally broad discussions of the social sciences; for example in 1990 the committee explored the idea of a Social Sciences Consortium.
      - Agendas and Minutes
        - 1949-1981, 25 folders (Box 7)
        - 1982-1990, 11 folders (Box 8)
        - January 1991-January 1992, 10 folders (Box 57)
          [ER RESTRICTED until December 1, 2033 ]
        - March 1993-June 1997, 10 folders (Box 58)
        - July 1997-February 2001, 10 folders (Box 59)
        - March 2001-February 2005, 13 folders (Box 60)
      - Miscellaneous
        - Notes from Meetings 1946-1954 (Box 9)
        - Lists of Members 1951-1980 (Box 9)
        - Membership Correspondence 1946-1988, 6 folders (Box 9)
    - Policy Committee Agendas, Minutes or Proceedings and Notes 1964-2001
      The Policy Committee was established in January 1964 as a separate committee from the Administrative Committee and was intended to focus on policy implementation in ISR. Policies addressed by the committee include policies for salaries, the maintenance and development of staff, and research policies. The minutes and agendas date from 1964 to 1975, although minutes and proceedings do not exist for all years.
      - 1964-1972, 10 folders (Box 9)
      - 1973-May 1975, 4 folders (Box 10)
      - 1988-1993, 12 folders (Box 62)
      - April 1993-September 1994, 15 folders (Box 63)
      - October 1994-December 1995, 14 folders (Box 64)
      - January 1996-April 1997, 15 folders (Box 65)
      - May 1997-October 1998, 15 folders (Box 66)
      - November 1998-December 1999, 13 folders (Box 67)
      - 2000, 10 folders (Box 68)
      - 2001, 9 folders (Box 69)
  - Reports and Policies 1958-2000
    Reports and Policies (1.5 linear feet) includes annual financial reports for scattered years from 1958 to 1984/85 and one report of the Inter-university Consortium of Political and Social Research dating from 1979. The reports in Miscellaneous include reports from various committees, including Employee Evaluation, Planning, and Public Relations. There are two folders of policies relating to ISR; additional information on ISR policies can be found within the director's topical files and SRC. Also includes ISR annual reports from 1983 to 2000.
    - Reports
      - Annual Financial Reports 1958-1984/85 (Box 10)
      - ICPSR 1979, 1984/85, 2 folders (Box 10)
      - Miscellaneous 1950-1968 (Box 10)
      - Annual Reports 1983-2000, 10 folders (Box 55)
    - Policies 1947-1967
      - Academic and Student Appointments (Box 10)
      - Foreign Scholars (Box 10)
      - General Funds (Box 10)
      - Indirect Costs (Box 10)
      - Leave Without Pay and Special Duty Assignments (Box 10)
      - Off Campus Assignments (Box 10)
      - Outside Income and Conflict of Interest (Box 10)
      - Overtime (Box 10)
      - Personnel Policies (Box 10)
      - Professional Meetings and Work Hours (Box 10)
      - Project Proposals (Box 10)
      - Publications and Records Management (Box 10)
      - Regents Proceedings Affecting ISR (Box 10)
      - Salary and Compensation (Box 10)
      - Staff Benefits and Class Attendance (Box 10)
      - Teaching Appointments and Reimbursement to ISR (Box 10)
      - Tenure (Box 10)
      - Travel Reimbursements (Box 10)
      - Visiting Scholars and Gifts to the University (Box 10)
  - Director's Files 1946-2013
    The Director's Files (15.2 linear feet) date from 1946 to 1986 and are primarily those of Thomas Juster and Angus Campbell but there is some material of Rensis Likert and David L. Featherman. Included in this subseries is: Correspondence; the Director's Advisory Committee; Federal Budget and National Priorities; Foundations, Associations and other Groups; Topical Files, University of Michigan; and United States Government Units.
    - Correspondence
      The largest portion of the correspondence files, which measure 1.5 feet, are arranged alphabetically and are primarily those of Angus Campbell, documenting communication with publishers, researchers, and former ISR employees, among others. The correspondence dates from 1952 to 1986 and there is some overlap between these correspondence files and the University of Michigan and Foundations segments of the Director's files. Of note is the folder of correspondence with Milton Moss who was funded by ISR from 1973 to 1975 to assist in communicating research findings to federal agencies which might find them relevant. There is also a folder relating to King Features, dating from 1972 to 1975, which documents an attempt to familiarize the public with the findings of social research through a syndicated column.
      - Alphabetical 1953-1986
        - A-D, 4 folders (Box 10)
        - E-W, 19 folders (Box 11)
      - David L. Featherman
        - Correspondence 1990-1992 (Box 52)
        - Correspondence 1997-August 2000, 7 folders (Box 52)
        - Correspondence September 2000-March 2003, 12 folders (Box 53)
        - Correspondence April 2003-December 2004, 9 folders (Box 54)
        - Budget circa 2001-2004 (Box 56)
        - Center Director's Meeting 2002, 2 folders (Box 56)
        - Detroit Area Study Reports 1988-2004, 2 folders (Box 56)
        - External Review Report 1996 (Box 56)
        - Five Year Planning Document 1997 (Box 56)
        - Fleming meeting 2002, 2 folders (Box 56)
        - Fellowships 1998-2002 (Box 56)
        - Fifteenth Anniversary 1997 (Box 56)
        - Project Hubble 2001-2002 (Box 56)
        - Ford Foundation Hubble Report (Box 56)
        - Hollinger Report (Box 56)
        - Kish, Leslie 2000 (Box 56)
        - Memorandum of Agreement 1989-2003 (Box 56)
        - National Advisory Council 1999-2000, 2 folders (Box 56)
        - Program in Survey Methodology 1999-2013 (Box 56)
        - Research Data Center 2000-2005 (Box 56)
        - Tobin Committee Report 1986 (Box 56)
        - AAPOR Heritage Interviews 2005, 2 videotapes VHS (TM) (Box 56)
      - International Visitors
        - 1971-1986, 7 folders (Box 11)
      - Memos to Staff
        - Center Directors 1976-1983 (Box 11)
        - Primary Research Staff 1977-1985 (Box 12)
          - Program Directors 1977-1986 (Box 12)
          - Senior Staff 1977-1981, 1986 (Box 12)
          - Staff 1978-1983 (Box 12)
          - Study Directors 1977-1981 (Box 12)
    - Director's Advisory Committee (DAC)
      Director's Advisory Committee (DAC) (1 linear foot) documents a committee formed in 1976 as a forum to advise the director on substantive long-range issues involving ISR. Initially five staff members representing the ISR program directors met twice a month in meetings open to any program director or senior study director. The function of the committee was to discuss and make recommendations about various subjects selected by the director. Topics discussed include programmatic review, promotion policies, and computing. DAC was discontinued during Juster's six-month leave in 1983 and upon his return he did not resume the committee but instead convened ad hoc groups of senior staff to discuss particular issues as they arose. These records are most useful for Juster's position papers on such issues as the functions and roles of the Centers and the Institute, Institute level reviews, and development activities.
      - Memorandum and Yearly Files
        - Memorandum 1976-1979,1982-1983 (Box 12)
      - 1976/77
        - Agenda (Box 12)
        - Affirmative Action (Box 12)
        - The Center for Research on Economic Development (CRED) (Box 12)
        - Development Plans (Box 12)
        - External Relationships (Box 12)
        - Graduate Student Research Assistants (GSRAs) (Box 12)
        - Hiring and Promotion Policies (Box 12)
        - Public Perceptions of Problems and Policies (Box 12)
        - Resource Allocation (Box 12)
        - Retirement Furloughs and Special Duty Assignments (Box 12)
      - 1977/78
        - Agenda (Box 12)
        - Affirmative Action (Box 12)
        - Functions and Roles of the Centers and the Institute (Box 12)
        - Graduate Student Research Assistants (GSRAs) (Box 12)
        - Library (Box 12)
        - Plans for Coming Year (Box 12)
        - Publications Policy (Box 12)
        - UM Capital Campaign (Box 12)
      - 1978/79
        - General (Box 12)
        - External Financing (Box 12)
        - Organizational Growth (Box 12)
        - Programmatic Review (Box 12)
        - Promotion Policies (Box 12)
      - 1979/80
        - Agendas and Miscellaneous (Box 12)
        - Building Program (Box 12)
        - Computing (Box 12)
        - Development Campaign (Box 12)
        - Organizational Structure (Box 12)
        - Outside Income (Box 12)
        - Primary Research Staff Appointments (Box 12)
        - Programmatic Review (Box 12)
        - Promotion to Tenure Rank (Box 12)
        - Recruitment/Hiring Policies (Box 12)
        - Research Agenda (Box 12)
        - Role of Primary Research Staff in Universities (Box 12)
        - Training Program (Box 12)
      - 1980/81
        - Agenda Setting (Box 12)
        - Decision Making (Box 12)
        - Funding (Box 12)
        - Growth, Size and Quality (Box 12)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 12)
        - Remote Job Entry Station (Box 12)
        - Recruitment (Box 12)
      - 1981/82
        - Agenda (Box 12)
        - Building Addition (Box 12)
        - Cost Containment (Box 12)
        - Dean's Fund (Box 12)
        - Development Activities (Box 12)
        - Funding Crisis (Box 12)
        - Growth, Size and Quality (Box 12)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 12)
        - Overhead (Box 12)
        - Recruitment and Promotion (Box 12)
        - Remote Job Entry Station (Box 12)
        - Retreat (Box 12)
    - Federal Budget and National Priorities
      The Federal Budget and National Priorities segment (.5 feet) documents the impact of the Reagan budget cuts on ISR and the initiatives the director and staff took to minimize those cuts. Included are interviews conducted by Patricia Gurin with business executives and foundation officers in the private sector and congressional testimony by ISR staff, as well as correspondence with congressional representatives. These records make apparent the severity of the impact of federal government funding cuts to ISR.
      - Correspondence 1980-1985, 5 folders (Box 13)
      - Congressional Correspondence 1981-1984, 3 folders (Box 13)
      - Congressional Testimony 1981-1982 (Box 13)
      - Legislative Aids Visit 1982 (Box 13)
    - Foundations, Associations, and Other Groups
      Foundations, Associations, and Other Groups (1.5 feet) documents efforts to secure funding sources as well as to develop ideas for research projects. The files are primarily those of Angus Campbell although there are some of Thomas Juster's. Worth noting are the files under National Science Foundation which include the successful proposal for a three-year-grant for $3.1 million. The grant was awarded to ISR in 1971 to provide the sustaining funds necessary to strengthen ISR as a national center for social science research, including expanding the national sampling operation, improving methods and technology, and providing better access to data.
      - Alfred P. Sloan Foundation 1983 (Box 13)
      - American Academy of Art and Sciences 1961-1980 (Box 13)
      - American Association for Public Opinion Research 1954, 1961-1965 (Box 13)
      - American Heritage Foundation 1962-1968 (Box 13)
      - American Psychological Association 1949-1980 (Box 13)
      - Breakthrough 1971 (Box 13)
      - Carnegie Corporation 1970 (Box 13)
      - Charles F. Kettering Foundation 1970-1971 (Box 13)
      - Council on Civic Education 1965-1966 (Box 13)
      - Ford Foundation 1960-1985 (Box 13)
      - Foundation for Child Development 1977 (Box 13)
      - Mott Foundation 1976-1984 (Box 13)
      - National Opinion Research Center 1972-1974 (Box 13)
      - National Science Foundation
        - 1968-1978 (Box 14)
        - 1981-1985, 2 folders (Box 14)
        - Institutional Support Grant
          - Proposal 1970 (Box 14)
          - Committee to Administer the Institutional Grant (CAIG)
            - Correspondence and Committee Notes
              - 1970-1975, 3 folders (Box 14)
          - Project Reports, 1974-75 (Box 14)
          - Proposals 1971 (Box 14)
          - SRC Committee Reports on Proposed Use of Funds 1971 (Box 14)
          - Final Report 1976 (Box 14)
      - Research Triangle Institute 1976 (Box 14)
      - Russell Sage Foundation 1972-1980 (Box 14)
      - Social Science Research Council 1971-1976 (Box 14)
      - Social and Community Planning Research 1974-1983 (Box 14)
      - Society for the Psychological Study of Social Issues (SPSSI) 1948-1957 (Box 14)
      - World Health Organization 1974-1977 (Box 14)
      - York University 1967-1980 (Box 14)
    - Topical Files
      The Topical Files (5 linear feet) date from 1946 to 1986 and are primarily those of Juster. They do contain material from earlier directors, notably the General Funds files. Although these files cover a variety of subject areas, there are several files of note. The Teaching Titles files and the Promotion Policy files are important for discussion of the relationship of ISR staff to the university and include discussions of tenure and compensation issues as they relate to ISR staff. The folders under Computers and Computing provide documentation of the use of computers at ISR. The Development folders document an effort by ISR to establish funding sources other than government agencies. The folder on Organizational Structure contains correspondence between Provost Adams and Rensis Likert regarding the establishment of ISR at UM. The Executive Officers visit files dating from 1976 to 1982 provide profiles of ISR prepared for visits by senior UM officials. Also of note are the folders on ISR staff retreats and the Visiting Site Committee folders. The 1986 report of the external review committee, known as the "Tobin Report," and the reaction and discussion following the report are useful for insight into the goals as well as strengths and weaknesses of ISR in the mid-1980s.
      - Affirmative Action 1978-1980 (Box 15)
      - Anniversary Celebrations
        - 10 Year Anniversary 1956 (Box 15)
      - Center for Political Studies 1968 (Box 15)
      - Committees
        - Central Services 1982 (Box 15)
        - Long Term Development 1978-1979 (Box 15)
        - Long Range Strategy 1980 (Box 15)
        - Research Support
          - Foundations 1981 (Box 15)
          - Industry 1981 (Box 15)
          - Political Impact 1981 (Box 15)
          - RFP Response 1981 (Box 15)
        - Structure and Norms 1985 (Box 15)
      - Computer Assisted Telephone Interviewing (CATI)
        - 1979-1980 (Box 15)
        - 1984-1985 (Box 15)
      - Computers and Computing
        - General 1972-1982 (Box 15)
        - Computer Coordinating Committee 1978-1981 (Box 15)
        - Computer Policy Committee 1975-1977 (Box 15)
        - Computer Services 1961-1970 (Box 15)
        - Direct Data Entry 1978 (Box 15)
        - Hierarchical 1976-1977 (Box 15)
        - Remote Job Entry Station 1981-1982 (Box 15)
        - Word Processing 1977 (Box 15)
        - Textbook draft, 10 folders (Box 61)
        - Textbook draft (Box 62)
        - Textbook draft (Box 69)
      - Center for Research on Utilization of Scientific Knowledge (CRUSK)
        - 1961-1973, 3 folders (Box 15)
        - 1976-1979 (Box 51)
      - Center for Research on Utilization of Scientific Knowledge
        - 1981 (Box 16)
        - 1984-1986 (Box 16)
      - Central Services, 1977 1982 (Box 16)
      - Cycles Research Project 1978-1982 (Box 16)
      - Development
        - Correspondence 1976-1984, 2 folders (Box 16)
        - Interview Notes 1982-1983 (Box 16)
        - MacArthur Foundation 1984 (Box 16)
        - Memorandum and Notes 1978-1984 (Box 16)
        - Visit of William Gorham of the Urban Institute 1983 (Box 16)
      - Education 1977-1978 (Box 16)
      - Energy Conservation 1976-1978
        - 1978 (Box 16)
        - 1980-1981 (Box 16)
        - 1982 (preparation material) (Box 16)
        - 1985 (Box 16)
        - Response Committee 1985 (Box 16)
      - Financial
        - Endowment Accounts 1985-1986 (Box 17)
        - General Funds
          - 1955-1974 (Box 17)
          - 1975-1980 (Box 17)
          - 1981-1984 (Box 17)
          - General 1964-1985 (Box 17)
          - Intra-University Correspondence 1977-1981 (Box 17)
      - Founder's Symposia
        - 1979 (honoring George Katona) (Box 17)
        - 1980 (honoring Rensis Likert) (Box 17)
        - 1981 (honoring Dorwin Cartwright) (Box 17)
        - 1983 (honoring Angus Campbell) (Box 17)
      - Freedom of Information Act and Open Meetings Bill 1977 (Box 17)
      - Funding 1978-1981 (Box 17)
      - Intercenter Programs 1959 (Box 17)
      - Katz-Newcomb Lecture 1985 (Box 17)
      - Market Opinion Research Corporation 1982 (Box 17)
      - National Longitudinal Study 1977 (Box 17)
      - National Science Foundation Site Visit 1977 (Box 17)
      - Organizational Structure 1946-1965 (Box 17)
      - Outside Activities 1977 (Box 17)
      - Planning 1955 (Box 17)
      - Promotion Policy 1976-1986 (Box 17)
      - Public Preferences 1977 (Box 17)
      - Publications Board and Division 1978-1979, 1981 (Box 17)
      - Research Topics 1976 (Box 17)
      - Retirement Celebrations 1986, undated (Box 17)
      - Retreat
        - 1981-1982 (Box 17)
        - 1984 (Box 17)
        - 1988 (Box 17)
      - Social Change 1976-1977, 1982 (Box 18)
      - Space and Building Issues 1963-1982 (Box 18)
      - State of Michigan Department of Energy 1976 (Box 18)
      - Strategic Planning 1983 (Box 18)
      - Survey Research Center
        - Coding Section 1957-1980 (Box 18)
        - Field Section 1978-1985 (Box 18)
        - Organizational Behavior Program 1977-1980 (Box 18)
        - Sampling Section 1955-1981 (Box 18)
        - Survey Methodology 1976-1978, 2 folders (Box 18)
      - Teaching Titles and Researcher Classification 1952-1962 (Box 18)
      - Time Use 1983 (Box 18)
      - Transportation and Technology 1979-1981 (Box 18)
      - Vietnam War Moratorium 1969-1970 (Box 18)
      - Visiting Committee Site Visit and External Review ("Tobin Report") 1986, 2 folders (Box 18)
      - Watts Lines 1976-1977 (Box 18)
    - University of Michigan
      The University of Michigan Files (1.25 linear feet) date from 1946 to 1986 and include the correspondence of three ISR directors: Likert, Campbell and Juster. The files document, in part, the interaction between ISR and other university units and the involvement of ISR in university-wide activities. Of note are the Provost file, which contains correspondence relating to the establishment of SRC at UM and the Vice President for Academic Affairs file, for discussions of the use of general funds and salary policies.
      - Center for Continuing Education for Women 1977 (Box 18)
      - Center for Human Growth and Development 1985 (Box 18)
      - Center for Public Policy Research on Organ Transplantation 1985 (Box 18)
      - Center for Research on Economic Development 1958-1977 (Box 18)
      - Chinese Delegation 1979 (Box 19)
      - College of Engineering 1962-1980 (Box 19)
      - College of Literature, Science and the Arts 1953-1954, 1963-1983 (Box 19)
      - Computing Center 1961-1967 (Box 19)
      - Department of Anthropology 1970 (Box 19)
      - Department of Economics 1979-1983 (Box 51)
      - Department of Journalism 1971, 1975 (Box 19)
      - Department of Psychology 1969-1980 (Box 19)
      - Department of Sociology 1957-1984 (Box 19)
      - Departmental/ISR Relations 1953-1981 (Box 19)
      - Development 1957-1986 (Box 19)
      - Division of Research and Development Administration 1984-1985 (Box 19)
      - Dorr, Harold 1958-1965 (Box 19)
      - Faculty Club Survey 1965 (Box 19)
      - Faculty Salary Study 1978 (Box 19)
      - Faculty Women's Club 1962, 1967 (Box 19)
      - Flint 1979 (Box 19)
      - Fresh Air Camp 1964 (Box 19)
      - Horace H. Rackham School of Graduate Studies 1965-1985 (Box 19)
      - Institute of Gerontology 1985 (Box 19)
      - Institute of Science and Technology 1960-1978 (Box 19)
      - Law School 1968-1981 (Box 19)
      - Library 1966, 1973 (Box 19)
      - Mental Health Research Institute 1958, 1960 (Box 19)
      - Office of the President 1967-1983 (Box 19)
      - Office of Research Administration 1958-1964 (Box 19)
      - Presidents Club 1967 (Box 19)
      - Press Club 1966 (Box 19)
      - Provost 1946-1947 (Box 19)
      - School of Business Administration 1957-1986 (Box 19)
      - School of Education 1956-1982 (Box 19)
      - School of Public Health 1967-1982 (Box 19)
      - Senate Assembly Committee 1950-1969 (Box 19)
      - Staff Benefits 1952-1964 (Box 19)
      - Technology-Based Industry Committee 1980-1982 (Box 19)
      - Television Center, 1969 1974 (Box 19)
      - University Seminars 1985 (Box 19)
      - Vice President for Academic Affairs 1972-1986, 2 folders (Box 20)
      - Vice President and Chief Financial Officer 1951-1970 (Box 20)
      - Vice President for Research 1960-1986, 2 folders (Box 20)
    - U.S. Government
      The U.S. Government Files. (.75 linear feet) document correspondence with funding agencies of ISR and date from 1958 to 1985.
      - Agency for International Development 1962-1971 (Box 20)
      - Bureau of Census 1969, 1980-1981 (Box 20)
      - Commission on Civil Rights 1973-1975 (Box 20)
      - Commission on Federal Statistics 1971 (Box 20)
      - Department of Defense 1958-1978 (Box 20)
      - Department of Health, Education, and Welfare 1963-1977 (Box 20)
      - Department of the Interior 1970 (Box 20)
      - Department of Labor 1966-1985 (Box 20)
      - Department of State 1966-1967 (Box 20)
      - Harris Bill S. 836 1966-1967 (Box 20)
      - Housing and Urban Development, 1968 1977 (Box 20)
      - National Institute of Mental Health 1958-1966 (Box 20)
      - Science Advisor 1978 (Box 20)
      - Small Business Administration 1977-1983 (Box 20)
      - Misc. 1964-1974 (Box 20)
  - Assistant Directors Topical Files 1949-1989